Center for Community Studies Records
M. E. Grenander Department of Special Collections and Archives
Center for Community Studies Records1946-1976
nam_ua652.004
Created in 1950 in part to study education in school districts. The Center's mission was to identify the research factors that aid in constructing and maintaining strong democratic communities and to promote such factors through education.
State University of New York at Albany. Center for Community Studies
14.2 cubic ft.
M. E. Grenander Department of Special Collections and Archives, University at Albany, SUNY
Access
Access to student material in Series 2 is restricted. Series 1 and Series 3 are unrestricted. Consult a staff member for details.
Red asterisks (***) denote restricted items.
Acquisition Information
All items in this collection were transferred to the University Libraries, M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections and Archives. 1988 June
Historical Note
In 1950, the Board of Trustees of the State University of New York accepted a proposal and a $10,000 grant from the Bureau of Intercultural Education for the academic year 1950-1951 and established a Center for Community Studies (CCS). The CCS had its headquarters at the New York State College for Teachers in Albany, New York, although its staff worked with all thirty-three affiliated institutions in the state university system. CCS was set up as a pilot organization with Dr. William E. Vickery, Professor of Intercultural Education, as its director. CCS’s mission was to identify through research factors that aid in constructing and maintaining strong democratic communities and to promote the factors through education. On the basis of modern research in the field of community studies, the staff of CCS chose two main areas in which to experiment. The first of these was rooted in the notion that democratic communities thrive when individuals feel that their input counts and when they believe that they have the right and responsibility to share in community life and to help make important decisions that affect them, their neighbors and their whole community. The second principal for CCS’s research was guided by the idea that communities become stronger when individuals balance their personal needs and desires with those of the community at large. Given the above principles, the staff of CCS set out to find ways to promote participation in community affairs, especially the decision-making process and actions that democratic citizenship imply. It also sought to aid individuals in developing the ability to live and work productively while crossing the lines of race, religion, ethnicity, and membership in socio-economic groups so as to promote the common welfare of the whole community.
One of the most interesting fields for carrying out its mission was teacher education, as it was assumed that all schools reach all of the children of all of the people. It was recognized that how good schools were as training grounds for good community living depended a great deal on their teachers. Consequently, CCS’s working hypothesis was that the field of community studies was an effective means of training such teachers. As an organization, it emphasized its role of alerting teachers to their responsibilities in order to promote better human understanding and constructive thinking in inter-group relations. Teachers were to help their students acquire the ideals, skills and patterns of living necessary for living and working together in a complex modern society. Thus, teachers were expected to become active participants in community affairs to show in their daily lives the respect for other people that characterizes the free, humane and enlightened citizen, and to make their classrooms laboratories where students would learn good citizenship by living it each day. Moreover, the staff of CCS believed strongly that experiences in community studies could not come from books alone. It was thought that undergraduates and teachers in service needed real first-hand experiences in community living under competent guidance and direction. It was also thought that without such guidance and direction, community experience could well discourage further community participation rather than stimulate increased activity in community affairs. In order to fulfill these purposes, the staff of CCS developed several projects in community study and human relations. Their work was carried out according to the interests, needs, and facilities of the participating colleges and communities. The programs of the Center for Community Studies included working with school people, members and affiliates of clubs and other organizations, government workers and officials, lay community leaders, and other community workers in solving problems that required the activation and mobilization of social forces, community interest, and citizen participation. The staff of CCS worked to develop a broader awareness and understanding in communities of individual and community needs. These aims were attained through: classes, workshops and seminars in community organizations during which participants would relate theory to specific problems in their communities; guidance counseling and leadership of specific efforts in a single community or neighborhood to define problems and propose solutions, and act upon them, including work of general and special nature relating to the effective functioning of groups, committees, clubs, associations, etc.; internships in community study and development during which students and others were placed as aids, interns, or in some other position in citizens’ councils or councils of community service so as to work, cooperate and observe; and research to inquire into the processes by which individuals cooperate to solve community problems and broaden their perceptions of community needs.
A key concept of CCS’s approach was the principle of action research developed by Kurt Lewin and his associates as they endeavored to find ways to work effectively toward rational social management and social engineering. Operating on the principles of action research, the Center for Community Studies consisted of three divisions. First, the State University Conference on Community Studies was made up of representatives of each of the eleven state teachers colleges of the State University of New York. This conference helped to formulate CCS policy, stimulated action-research programs on local college campuses, and distributed information about CCS and its activities to other members of their respective faculties. The second division was a five-person executive committee drawn from this Conference whose duties were to screen projects submitted to CCS for support through grants in-aid and to allocate funds to local programs. The Executive Committee also defined issues and problems to present to the Conference for policy decisions. The third was the staff of CCS whose function was to coordinate the program, provide consultant services, administer the research fund, and help the local college communities interpret the program to their colleges. The staff also engaged in research at the colleges and helped the local communities prepare their reports for publication and distribution.
According to the undergraduate and graduate bulletins for the State University of New York at Albany, the Center for Community Studies ceased to exist as a separate entity from the School of Education between the fall of 1964 and the spring of 1966. Its programs and research seem to have been absorbed and restructured as an integral part of the School of Education.
This collection documents the organization, evolution, scope, thinking, activities and programs of the Center for Community Studies over a period of about 25 years. The earliest items contained in this collection date from 1825 and were part of the Census Classification Project for Albany, New York, but continuous records for the CCS itself start at its inception in 1950 and continue to the apparent date of its disbanding. There are also some records, mostly memos and letters, that postdate the apparent discontinuation of CCS that run up to 1976. Major collectors of records appear to be professors William E. Vickery and Donald Van Cleve.
Topics which are extensively documented in this collection include action research projects, extensive course materials, the Three Wishes Project, the development of educational television, the New York State Citizens’ Council, the Poliomyelitis Project of 1956, in-school testing materials, student and faculty questionnaires, materials on different areas in which CCS was of service to the wider community, student papers, the Study of Opinions on Medicine and Child Health of 1956, the University-Community Cooperation Project and materials on workshops given by CCS. Also contained in this collection are photocopies of street maps of Albany, New York from the 1800s and early 1900s.
Several collections in the M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections and Archives provide further information on education and policy issues that were of concern to the faculty, staff and students of the Center for Community Studies. For complete listings of related collections, consult the subject guides for University at Albany, SUNY Administrative Records and Education. Of particular note are the records of the Capital Area School Development Association (APAP065) and the School of Education (UA650).
Arrangement of the Collection
The collection is unprocessed and is likely disorganized. Individual items may be difficult to find.
Subject and Genre Headings
Neighborhood and Community Associations; Medicine and Health Care; Ethnic Groups; State University of New York at Albany; Teacher education
Container List
- Administrative Files, 1950-1976; nam_ua652.004-1; 1 cubic ft.
  This series consists of materials relating directly to the operations of the Center for Community Studies and to some of its faculty and staff. The series includes: the records of the activities and programs committees; minutes of the American Red Cross, Albany, New York chapter; Board of Directors of the Council of Community Services; the Inter-group Relations Committee; the Siesta Symposium of 1966; the Subcommittee of the New York State Citizens' Council Field Committee; the Superintendents' Advisory Committee; records pertaining to faculty and staff meetings; alumni; personnel; and recruitment strategies. Other items found in this series include budget materials, Executive Committee meetings, expense accounts, grants, memoranda, and records concerning the Temporary Committee on Graduate Admissions.
  Arranged alphabetically.
  - Addresses, Undated; nam_ua652.004-1_1 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Admissions, 1964; nam_ua652.004-1_2 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Advisory Committee, 1952-1962; nam_ua652.004-1_3 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Advisory Committee on Social Work Administration, 1963-1964; nam_ua652.004-1_4 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Advisory Group of School Superintendents, 1963; nam_ua652.004-1_5 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Albany Community Chest, Undated; nam_ua652.004-1_6 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Alphabetical List of Agencies, Undated; nam_ua652.004-1_7 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Alumni, 1966; nam_ua652.004-1_8 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - American Red Cross, Undated; nam_ua652.004-1_9 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Annual Report, Undated; nam_ua652.004-1_10 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Annual Report of the Director, 1951; nam_ua652.004-1_11 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Annual Report of the Director, Undated; nam_ua652.004-1_12 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Annual Report of the Director, 1952; nam_ua652.004-1_13 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Annual Research Convocation, 1962; nam_ua652.004-1_14 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Awards, 1975; nam_ua652.004-1_15 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Bibliography, Undated; nam_ua652.004-1_16 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Board of Directors, Undated; nam_ua652.004-1_17 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Budget, 1952-1954; nam_ua652.004-1_18 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Campus Academic Plan, Undated; nam_ua652.004-1_19 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Classification System, Undated; nam_ua652.004-1_20 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Committee for May Dinner, 1951-1952; nam_ua652.004-1_21 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Committee on Administration, 1951; nam_ua652.004-1_22 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Committee on Advanced Programs, 1976; nam_ua652.004-1_23 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Committee on Advanced Studies in Education, 1966; nam_ua652.004-1_24 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Committee on Doctoral Programs in Education, 1960-1964; nam_ua652.004-1_25 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Committee on Intergroup Relations 1952-54, Undated; nam_ua652.004-1_26 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Committee Reports, Undated; nam_ua652.004-1_27 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Cooperation with Social Science Division, 1964; nam_ua652.004-1_28 (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Department of Education, 1956; nam_ua652.004-1_29 (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Department of Foundations of Education, 1966-1967; nam_ua652.004-1_30 (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Directory, Undated; nam_ua652.004-1_31 (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Dissertation Seminar Committee, 1963-1964; nam_ua652.004-1_32 (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - Executive Committee Meetings, 1952-1953; nam_ua652.004-1_33 (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - Expense Accounts, Undated; nam_ua652.004-1_34 (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - Faculties Association, 1962; nam_ua652.004-1_35 (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - Faculty Meetings, 1964-1966; nam_ua652.004-1_36 (Box 1, Folder 36)
  - Faculty Meetings, Undated; nam_ua652.004-1_37 (Box 1, Folder 37)
  - Faculty, Undated; nam_ua652.004-1_38 (Box 1, Folder 38)
  - Graduate Academic Council, 1964-1967; nam_ua652.004-1_39 (Box 1, Folder 39)
  - Graduate Sequence Committee, 1962; nam_ua652.004-1_40 (Box 1, Folder 40)
  - Grants, 1963; nam_ua652.004-1_41 (Box 1, Folder 41)
  - Guidelines for Certification, Undated; nam_ua652.004-1_42 (Box 1, Folder 42)
  - History and Mission, 1953; nam_ua652.004-1_43 (Box 1, Folder 43)
  - Intergroup Relations Committee, Undated; nam_ua652.004-1_44 (Box 1, Folder 44)
  - Memoranda, 1964-1973; nam_ua652.004-1_45 (Box 1, Folder 45)
  - New York State Association of Councils and Chests, Undated; nam_ua652.004-1_46 (Box 1, Folder 46)
  - New York State Citizens Council Field Committee, Undated; nam_ua652.004-1_47 (Box 1, Folder 47)
  - Nominating Committee, Undated; nam_ua652.004-1_48 (Box 1, Folder 48)
  - Personnel, 1966-1967; nam_ua652.004-1_49 (Box 1, Folder 49)
  - Personnel, Undated; nam_ua652.004-1_50 (Box 1, Folder 50)
  - Policy and Procedures on Continuing Appointments, 1972; nam_ua652.004-1_51 (Box 1, Folder 51)
  - Problems Census Committee, 1950-1951; nam_ua652.004-1_52 (Box 1, Folder 52)
  - Recruitment, 1964-1965; nam_ua652.004-1_53 (Box 1, Folder 53)
  - Siesta Symptoms, Undated; nam_ua652.004-1_54 (Box 1, Folder 54)
  - Staff Meetings, 1951-1952; nam_ua652.004-1_55 (Box 1, Folder 55)
  - State University Committee on Community Studies, 1956; nam_ua652.004-1_56 (Box 1, Folder 56)
  - Subcommittee on Organization and Homemaker Study Committee, 1956; nam_ua652.004-1_57 (Box 1, Folder 57)
  - Superintendents Advisory Committee and the Faculty in Educational Administration, Undated; nam_ua652.004-1_58 (Box 1, Folder 58)
  - Temporary Committee on Graduate Admissions, 1973; nam_ua652.004-1_59 (Box 1, Folder 59)
  - Vita, Undated; nam_ua652.004-1_60 (Box 1, Folder 60)
  - Advisory Committee Meetings, 1952; nam_ua652.004-1_61 (Box 14, Folder 1)
  - Annual Report of the Center for Community Studies, 1951-1952; nam_ua652.004-1_62 (Box 14, Folder 2)
  - Staff Meetings, 1952; nam_ua652.004-1_63 (Box 14, Folder 3)
- Activities and Programs, 1825-1976; nam_ua652.004-2; 12 cubic ft.
  Student material is restricted, must consult archivist to view material.
  This series contains materials relating directly to the activities and programs of the Center for Community Studies. Topics of interest include action research projects, extensive course materials, the Three Wishes Project, the development of educational television, the New York State Citizens' Council, the Poliomyelitis Project of 1956, in-school testing materials, student and faculty questionnaires and study notes, materials on different areas in which CCS was of service to the wider community, student papers and projects, the Study of Opinions on Medicine and Child Health of 1956, the University-Community Cooperation Project, and materials on workshops given by CCS. This series is restricted due to the inclusion of student material. Consult a member of the Department of Special Collections and Archives' staff for further details.
  - Abrams, Charles, Chapter 2: "Implications of the Studies", Undated; nam_ua652.004-2_1 (Box 1, Folder 61)
  - Academic Freedom, 1952-1954; nam_ua652.004-2_2 (Box 1, Folder 62)
  - Action for Cultural Enrichment Project, Undated; nam_ua652.004-2_3 (Box 1, Folder 63)
  - Action Research, Brockport State Teachers College, 1951; nam_ua652.004-2_4 (Box 1, Folder 64)
  - Action Research, Buffalo State Teachers College, 1951-1952; nam_ua652.004-2_5 (Box 1, Folder 65)
  - Action Research, Fredonia State Teachers College, 1951-1953; nam_ua652.004-2_6 (Box 1, Folder 66)
  - Action Research, Geneseo State Teachers College, 1952-1953; nam_ua652.004-2_7 (Box 1, Folder 67)
  - Action Research, Oneonta State Teachers College, 1951; nam_ua652.004-2_8 (Box 1, Folder 68)
  - Action Research, State Teachers College Oswego, 1951; nam_ua652.004-2_9 (Box 1, Folder 69)
  - The ADA Craig Walker Award, Undated; nam_ua652.004-2_10 (Box 1, Folder 70)
  - Student, SOC 110: Intergroup Relations, 1951; nam_ua652.004-2_11 (Box 1, Folder 71)
  - Albany AAUP, 1963-1964; nam_ua652.004-2_12 (Box 1, Folder 72)
  - Albany Adult Education Department, 1953; nam_ua652.004-2_13 (Box 1, Folder 73)
  - Albany Council of Community Services, Undated; nam_ua652.004-2_14 (Box 1, Folder 74)
  - Albany Community Chest Project, 1948-1951; nam_ua652.004-2_15 (Box 1, Folder 75)
  - Albany Community Project, Undated; nam_ua652.004-2_16 (Box 1, Folder 76)
  - Albany County Department of Health, Annual Report, 1953; nam_ua652.004-2_17 (Box 1, Folder 77)
  - Albany Neighborhood Study, 1954; nam_ua652.004-2_18 (Box 1, Folder 78)
  - Student, SOC 110: Intergroup Relations, 1952; nam_ua652.004-2_19 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Student, Student Report, 1951; nam_ua652.004-2_20 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - American Association of Colleges for Teacher Education, 1952; nam_ua652.004-2_21 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - American Cyanamid Company, 1951; nam_ua652.004-2_22 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Analysis of Three Wishes Project, 1952; nam_ua652.004-2_23 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Annual Curriculum Conference for School Administrations, Undated; nam_ua652.004-2_24 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - The Association for Supervision and Curriculum Development, 1953; nam_ua652.004-2_25 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Student, 1951; nam_ua652.004-2_26 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Bard, B, "Guide for Future Teachers," New York Post, 1961 February 27; nam_ua652.004-2_27 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Student, "An Analysis of the Heavenly City of the Eighteenth Century Philosphers", Undated; nam_ua652.004-2_28 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Student, "Friedrich Froebel", 1976; nam_ua652.004-2_29 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Student, "The Theory of Michael De Montaigne, 1976; nam_ua652.004-2_30 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Student, SOC 408 Final Exam, 1961; nam_ua652.004-2_31 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Berger, M.I., "School and Society", 1957; nam_ua652.004-2_32 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Student, "School Taxes and Public Relations", 1952; nam_ua652.004-2_33 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Student, Education 317 Report, 1951; nam_ua652.004-2_34 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Bibliographies, 1953-1954; nam_ua652.004-2_35 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Bibliography for Local History, 1952-1953; nam_ua652.004-2_36 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Book Fair, Undated; nam_ua652.004-2_37 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Books on Reserve, 1949; nam_ua652.004-2_38 (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Student,, "Television as a Medium of Education and Its Role in Educational Public Relations", 1952; nam_ua652.004-2_39 (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - The Brockport Delinquency Conference, 1955; nam_ua652.004-2_40 (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Brown School, Student Subjects, Undated; nam_ua652.004-2_41 (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - Brubacher, John S. "A Proposal for Judging What Is and What Is Not Progressive Education", 1956; nam_ua652.004-2_42 (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - Student, Education 301A: Philosophy of Education, 1957; nam_ua652.004-2_43 (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - Bureau for Intercultural Education, 1950-1952; nam_ua652.004-2_44 (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - Student, Student Project, 1976; nam_ua652.004-2_45 (Box 2, Folder 27)
  - Cali, A.J., Some Observations Concerning the School Administration and Public Problems in the Sixties, 1960; nam_ua652.004-2_46 (Box 2, Folder 28)
  - Student, Project and Exam, 1961; nam_ua652.004-2_47 (Box 2, Folder 29)
  - Camp Rising Sun, Louis A. Jonas Foundation, 1950-1952; nam_ua652.004-2_48 (Box 2, Folder 30)
  - Campo, Anthony, SOC 408 Final Exam, 1961; nam_ua652.004-2_49 (Box 2, Folder 31)
  - Capital Area School Boards Institute, Undated; nam_ua652.004-2_50 (Box 2, Folder 32)
  - Capital Area School Development Association, 1955-1956; nam_ua652.004-2_51 (Box 2, Folder 33)
  - Capital Area School Development Association, Human Relations through English Group, 1952; nam_ua652.004-2_52 (Box 2, Folder 34)
  - Capital Area School Development Association, Workshop, 1951; nam_ua652.004-2_53 (Box 2, Folder 35)
  - The Case for Modern Man, 1963-1965; nam_ua652.004-2_54 (Box 2, Folder 36)
  - Student, Educational Philosophy 601, 1976; nam_ua652.004-2_55 (Box 2, Folder 37)
  - Center for Intergroup Education, the University of Chicago, 1949; nam_ua652.004-2_56 (Box 2, Folder 38)
  - Central New York School Study Council, 1964; nam_ua652.004-2_57 (Box 2, Folder 39)
  - Childs, John L. "John Dewey and Education", Undated; nam_ua652.004-2_58 (Box 2, Folder 40)
  - The Citizens Advisory Committee on Housing, Research Report No. 1, 1953; nam_ua652.004-2_59 (Box 2, Folder 41)
  - Citizens Committee for Albany Public Schools, 1953; nam_ua652.004-2_60 (Box 2, Folder 42)
  - Student, SOC 110: Intergroup Relations, 1951; nam_ua652.004-2_61 (Box 2, Folder 43)
  - Clark, Norman, Director of Clinton Square Neighborhood House, 1951; nam_ua652.004-2_62 (Box 2, Folder 44)
  - Student, Education 317, 1951; nam_ua652.004-2_63 (Box 2, Folder 45)
  - Code Sheet Project X Stencil, Undated; nam_ua652.004-2_64 (Box 2, Folder 46)
  - Student, "An Exploratory Study of the Status of Hierarchy of Selected High School Occupations", 1963; nam_ua652.004-2_65 (Box 2, Folder 47)
  - Student, SOC 110: Intergroup Relations, 1951; nam_ua652.004-2_66 (Box 2, Folder 48)
  - The College Study in Intergroup Relations by Lloyd Allen Cook, 1946; nam_ua652.004-2_67 (Box 2, Folder 49)
  - Collegiate Association for Development of Educational Administration in New York State (CADEA), 1962-1964; nam_ua652.004-2_68 (Box 2, Folder 50)
  - Colloquia, 1976; nam_ua652.004-2_69 (Box 2, Folder 51)
  - Student, Education 317, 1951; nam_ua652.004-2_70 (Box 2, Folder 52)
  - Community Analysis, 1962-1967; nam_ua652.004-2_71 (Box 2, Folder 53)
  - Community Colleges and Institutes, State University of New York, Undated; nam_ua652.004-2_72 (Box 2, Folder 54)
  - Community Leadership and Development, 1952-1954; nam_ua652.004-2_73 (Box 2, Folder 55)
  - Community Legal Rights Foundation, Inc., 1972; nam_ua652.004-2_74 (Box 2, Folder 56)
  - Community Research, 1962; nam_ua652.004-2_75 (Box 2, Folder 57)
  - Community Resources for Education, 1952-1953; nam_ua652.004-2_76 (Box 2, Folder 58)
  - Community Studies, 1953-1957; nam_ua652.004-2_77 (Box 2, Folder 59)
  - Community Study Core Report, 1963-1964; nam_ua652.004-2_78 (Box 2, Folder 60)
  - Community Study and Development, Undated; nam_ua652.004-2_79 (Box 2, Folder 61)
  - Comparative Education Society, 1968; nam_ua652.004-2_80 (Box 2, Folder 62)